"Mixed Nuts Put to the Test
for Erectile Dysfunction"
In 2013 — I can't believe it's already
been so long — I posted a video
based on this study, that found that
three weeks of pistachios resulted
in a significant improvement
in erectile function in men.
It's always nice to see a whole food
intervention have clinical effects,
and I was curious to revisit the topic
to see what's been published since.
Even if you ignore all the lab
animal studies on, you know,
how much hazelnuts improve
the function of rat testicles,
you still never know what you'll find
searching the medical literature
for nuts and sexual function,
like this case of penile
strangulation with a metal hex nut.
I guess nuts can sometimes make
things worse if you can't remove them.
They used the Dundee technique, which
involves creating 20 puncture holes
to relieve the pressure,
but that didn't work.
So a diamond disk cutter
was used to saw through it,
and they slipped a few times.
All's well that ends well.
Well, that got me curious.
Evidently, penile entrapment
is so common,
there's an entire grading system
that emergency room docs can use.
If a drill is not available,
these surgeons advise
a hammer and chisel may be used.
A drill? Oh, a dental drill.
I like how they brag about
the precisely cut edges.
Looks pretty jagged to me.
To "preserve the penis
from a fatal outcome"
(that's a strange way to put it),
urologists should be aware of all
the available armamentarium,
and if you don't know how
to operate the saw,
you can always call in
your local blacksmith.
Yet, how are you going to remove a
barbell or steel sledgehammer head?
A heavy-duty air grinder provided by
the fire department, requiring 6 hours
of cutting, with the patient protected
from the sparks with fire coats
whatever it takes.
Hack saw. Cement eater.
Or the silk winding method.
But anyway, back
to the task at hand.
Consumption of at least one serving
of vegetables a day and more than
two servings of nuts a week
was associated with more than
a 50% decrease in the probability
of erectile dysfunction
in a snapshot-in-time
cross-sectional study.
But such observational studies
can't prove cause-and-effect.
It's like finding that men who eat more
healthfully have better swimmers.
Maybe men who eat nuts
are just health nuts,
and the improvement is due to
some other factor like exercise.
What we need is an interventional
trial, and here we go.
The effect of nut consumption on
semen quality and functionality:
a randomized controlled trial.
A Standard American Diet, with
or without a handful of walnuts,
and a half handful of each
almonds and hazelnuts.
And the nut group experienced
significant improvements
in their total sperm count,
vitality, motility, and shape,
perhaps because those
in the nut group
showed a significant reduction
in SDF: sperm DNA fragmentation.
The nuts appeared to
protect their sperm DNA.
Too bad while they were at it,
they didn't measure the guys'
erectile and sexual dysfunction.
Oh, but they did!
The effect of nut consumption on erectile
and sexual function from the same study.
The researchers report that those in
the nut group saw a significant increase
in orgasmic function and sexual desire,
but what about erectile function?
Any time you see this kind of
selective glass-half-full reporting
you suspect some kind
of industry funding,
and indeed that was the case here.
Yes, there was a marginal increase in
orgasmic function and sexual desire
of questionable clinical significance,
but no improvement in erectile function,
intercourse satisfaction,
or overall satisfaction.
And with so many comparisons,
even the so-called significant findings
may not even be
statistically significant.
But why did the pistachios
I talked about back in 2013 work,
while these other nuts didn't?
Well, if you remember, the
original study was done on men
in their 40s and 50s who already
had chronic erectile dysfunction,
whereas the average age in
the new study was 24 years old.
So they may have started out
with near-maximum circulation,
not leaving much
room for the nuts.